Guide to the Paul A. Samuelson papers, 1933-2010 and undated RL.10082
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Unpublished Writings Series, 1933-2009 and undated, 26 boxes
  - Uncategorized Unpublished Writings, 1933-2007 and undated
    - Demand and supply oligopoly, undated (Box 150)
    - Demand for commodities, not demand for labour?, 1977 (Box 150)
    - The demand for partial information, 1985 (Box 150)
    - Democracy and Mixed Capitalism (probably published), 1980 (Box 150)
    - Determinateness of economic equilibrium (inequalities and equalities, fixed-point theorems, extrema, independent conditions, and unknowns), 1982 (Box 150)
    - Do you have talent for economic theory?, undated (Box 150)
    - Does Expected Utility maximizing have survival value?, 1986 (Box 150)
    - Does history differ from permanent hysteresis?, 1971 (Box 150)
    - Double-switching, after all, is "Intertemporally Pareto-Optimal," undated (Box 151)
    - Duopoly and the theory of games, undated (Box 151)
    - Dynamic aspects of linear models of production: generalize Leontief systems, undated (Box 151)
    - Economic forecasting and national policy, 1956 (Box 151)
    - Economics as a Career, Moving Up, 1988 (Box 151)
    - Economics of joint cost, undated (Box 151)
    - Entropy rise as merely regression toward the mean, 1982 (Box 151)
    - An essay on money and debt, undated (Box 151)
    - Exact time reversibility despite Galtonian regression toward the mean, 1990 (Box 151)
    - Excursus on utility and probability, undated (Box 151)
    - The fable of the 4 braintrusters and the determinateness of duopoly, undated (Box 151)
    - Factor and commodity prices in general equilibrium, 1950, 1953 (Box 151)
    - A fragmentary note on the equilibrium of the firm, 1935-1936 (Box 151)
    - General joint production, 1984 (Box 151)
    - General point-rationing analysis under standard demand conditions, 1985 (Box 151)
    - Gold again, 1980s (Box 151)
    - The half loaf worse than non: case study of partial reform's inefficiency, 1982 (Box 151)
    - Horn of Plenty (story), 1930s (Box 151)
    - Impressionistic history of the U.S. rate of return on capital, 1983 (Box 151)
    - Infinity, unanimity, and singularity: A rejoinder (probably published), 1959 (Box 151)
    - Interest rate equilization, 1976 (Box 151)
    - Kernel of the convolution type (Volterra), undated (Box 152)
    - The limitations of collective bargaining, 1933-1934 (Box 152)
    - Linearity of Engel's curves and gambler's indifference, undated (Box 152)
    - Literary, mathematical, graphical criteria for complementarity, undated (Box 152)
    - Many-variable factor-price frontiers, with or without the profit rate, 1973 (Box 152)
    - Microscopic time asymmetry of Maxwell's Demon, 1985 (Box 152)
    - Minimalist translations of Schumpeter's analyses: any dark sides to "creative capitalist destruction"?, 2007 (Box 152)
    - The More General Substitution Theorem, 1975 (Box 152)
    - The new economics, 1969 (Box 152)
    - New foundations for the pure theory of consumer's behavior, 1930s (Box 152)
    - A note on price determination by a discrimination monopolist subject to differential costs in different markets, 1935 (Box 152)
    - Note on similarity between duopoly and bilateral monopoly, undated (Box 152)
    - Notes on foreign press article, 1984 (Box 152)
    - Notes on Keynes's probability, 1975 (Box 152)
    - On a problem of Weiszacker (Box 152)
    - On cardinal measurability of temperature, undated (Box 152)
    - On, 1964 (Box 152)
    - On Norbert Wiener, 1964 (Box 152)
    - Notes on the monetary measures and objectives, 1939 (Box 152)
    - The Optimality property of the biological rate of interest, 1959 (Box 152)
    - Pareto-Chipman Theorem, 1996 (Box 152)
    - The period of production in intertemporal production processes, 1980 (Box 152)
    - Personal file, 1937-1995 (Box 152)
    - Post-war planning as seen by a retired post-war planner, 1940s (Box 152)
    - Probability in conservative and damped ecological fluctuations, 1974 (Box 152)
    - The Production function and the Laws of Returns, 1930s (Box 152)
    - Profit through exchange, undated (Box 152)
    - The Quarterly Journal of Economics at 100, 1986 (Box 152)
    - Rationality of the Corn-Hog Cycle, 1975 (Box 152)
    - Reswitching in a one-department model, 1981 (Box 152)
    - The scientists take over, undated (Box 152)
    - The selfish economy, 1997 (Box 152)
    - Signs of Spring, 1978 (Box 152)
    - Simple intuitive proofs of neoclassical functions admitting of capital aggregation, 1965 (Box 152)
    - Some aspects of the origins and evolutions of his economic ideas, by P.A.S. in response to Donald A. Walker, 1992-1995 (Box 152)
    - Sketch of an exact model of money, 1972 (Box 153)
    - Some deducible parallels between continuum marginal productivity technologies and limited sustainability technologies, 2005 (Box 153)
    - Some influences of Vito Volterra (1860-1940), 1984 (Box 153)
    - Speculations on altruism as a factor in economic life, 1972 (Box 153)
    - Summary of general equilibrium with variable production, undated (Box 153)
    - The theory of demand under rationing of goods, undated, 3 folders (Box 153)
    - Time reversibility of one-dimensional hard balls, 1968 (Box 153)
    - Transformation problem with joint products, undated (Box 153)
    - 24 causes of human misjudgment, undated (Box 153)
    - Two Kaldorian tours de force, 1987 (Box 153)
    - Two theorems on non-substitution and substitution and related dialogues, 1979 (Box 153)
    - Ultimate Non-Substitution Theorem and Factor Price Equalisation Theorem are one, 1989 Aug. (Box 153)
    - The unavoidable inefficiency of partial deregulation and partial land reforms, 1979 (Box 153)
    - Uniqueness of permanent economic equilibrium for high-saving systems, 1970 (Box 153)
    - Untitled (risk and double switching), undated (Box 153)
    - Valuation of factors of production, 1951 (Box 153)
    - Victory of the mixed economy, 1989 (Box 153)
    - Weighting in the compounding of probabilities, 1944 (Box 153)
    - When standard commodities do and don't exist, 1983 (Box 153)
    - Why economists disagree, undated (Box 153)
    - Worker capitalism Scandinavian style, 1982 (Box 153)
    - World War first in a century, undated (Box 153)
  - Notes and Fragments, 1937-2009 and undated
    Conditions Governing Access
    Fragmentary notes, drafts, and files created by Samuelson throughout his career. Some folders contain handwritten notebook pages or notebooks on a specific topic. Alphabetically arranged by original title or topic.
    - Aggregation degeneracy (Pasinetti), undated (Box 154)
    - Alleged advantages of operational methods, undated (Box 154)
    - Aspects of the 1941 Stolper-Samuelson collaboration, 2002 (Box 154)
    - Assertion and fallacy in demand analysis, 1945 (Box 154)
    - Calculus of diversity, 1991 (Box 154)
    - A cold comfort theorem (on automation), undated (Box 154)
    - Commenter's code of duty, undated (Box 154)
    - Comparative advantage, 2006 (Fortune Magazine) (Box 154)
    - Competitive wage/profit sharing in jigsaw double helix technologies, 2005 (Box 154)
    - Consumer surplus, undated (Box 154)
    - Constructive generalization of Hawkins-Simon tests for a joint-product system to be productive, 1984 (Box 154)
    - Correcting misunderstanding of Laurent's valid query, undated (Box 154)
    - A critique of Canning's proposed method, undated (Box 154)
    - Data analysis tables and figures, 2002-2003; 1.5 Megabytes; 2 PDF document files and 6 BMP image files; approximately 1 megabytes.
    - Defanging double reswitching and understanding its temporal-Pareto optimality, 1990s (Box 154)
    - Diagnosing and correcting a subset of fundamental errors in more heat than light, undated (Box 154)
    - Digital demand, 1963 (Box 154)
    - A digression on minimizing regret, undated (Box 154)
    - Does Laissez-Faire maximize the well-being of the "random" individual?, undated (Box 154)
    - Double-switching, after all, is intertemporally Pareto-optimal, 2004 (Box 154)
    - Economic post mortem, 1970s (Box 154)
    - Efficiency economics, undated (Box 154)
    - The essentiality of uniform profit rates, 1988 Aug (Box 154)
    - Evsey D. Domar (1914-1997), 1998 (Box 154)
    - Extending non-substitution theorem to certain durable-capital models, undated (Box 154)
    - Foreword to Chinese translation of Foundations (published), 1988 (Box 154)
    - Foreword to Japanese Vol. 7 (Keiso volume), translated into Japanese (probably published), 1991 (Box 154)
    - Further considerations of the transfer problem, undated (Box 154)
    - A girl called Alma (Harvard), undated (Box 154)
    - A golden rule of pricing, 1964 (Box 154)
    - Hawkins-Simon and all that, undated (Box 154)
    - Heuristics on the essentiality of uniform profit rate for intertemporal efficiency, undated (Box 154)
    - Hollander, 1992 (Box 154)
    - Homage to Samuel Hollander: petite numerical bonbons in the Malthus saga, 2006 (Box 154)
    - How an ethical monotonicity axiom discredits itself, 1988 (Box 154)
    - How the commodity of money needed to go, 1994 (Box 154)
    - Is the Krugman Heresy heresy? How third world productivity advance will presumably affect first world affluence, undated (Box 154)
    - Kaldor's machines-slaves-bread model, undated (Box 154)
    - The Knight-Kaldor-Von Neumann imbroglio resolved by the Leontief two-period capital model, undated (Box 154)
    - Laplacian, 2005 (Box 154)
    - Laws I and II: Bottom of the bottom line, undated (Box 154)
    - Law of diminishing returns, undated (Box 154)
    - Law of falling rate of profit and rising real wage, undated (Box 154)
    - A life on the frontier of the new non-dismal economics, undated (Box 154)
    - List of worries (U.S. economic situation), undated (Box 154)
    - Magic Mountain (or Los Alamos), 2007 (Box 154)
    - Marshall's Achilles heel, 1989 June (Box 154)
    - Mathematic derivations, undated (Box 154)
    - Maximal individual fitness and maximal group fitness in a Nash equilibrium that maximizes nothing, undated (Box 154)
    - Memorandum on investment (to Seymour Harris), 1964 (Box 154)
    - Method of continuous substitution, undated (Box 154)
    - Microscopic time-irreversibility and macroscopic time reversibility, undated (Box 154)
    - Minimalist translations of Schumpeter's Analyses: Any dark sides to creative capitalist destruction? (Box 154)
    - Miscellaneous notes on economic policy, undated (Box 154)
    - Nassau Senior was not dead wrong after all!, 1997 (Box 154)
    - National income accounting when labor skills are produced inputs, undated (Box 154)
    - A needed proof of a plausible basic conjecture, 1996 (Box 154)
    - Nicholas Kaldor, 1988 (Box 154)
    - Notes on the theory of expectations, undated (Box 154)
    - No, the economy is not benefited by price instability, undated (Box 154)
    - The non-measurability of utility, undated (Box 154)
    - A non-substitution theorem for systems without primary factors, 1987 (Box 154)
    - Notebook, Kaldor (Post-Keynesian), undated (Box 154)
    - Arc elasticity of demand, 1930s (Box 154)
    - Notes on G.W. Mackey, Unitary Group Representations in Physics, Probability, and Number Theory, undated (Box 154)
    - Notes on Hotelling matrix paper, undated (Box 154)
    - Notes on the Le Chatelier Principle, 1956 (Box 154)
    - Notes on Mark Mitnitzky, Aspects of Government Spending, 1943 (Box 154)
    - Notes on monetary measures and objectives, 1939 (Box 154)
    - Notes on Pareto's Cours de Economie Politique, undated (Box 155)
    - Notes on Ramsey for paper on model, undated (Box 155)
    - Notes on statistical decisions, undated (Box 155)
    - Notes on Swedish economic conditions, 1948 (Box 155)
    - Notes on the economics of hyper-deflation (Box 155)
    - Notes on Norwegian economy, 1948 (Box 155)
    - Notes on the problem of stock market production, undated (Box 155)
    - Notes on Viner, 1937 (Box 155)
    - Notes on Willard Gibbs, undated (Box 155)
    - Oligopoly self-contradictions: comment on Kawamata's consistent conjectures oligopoly equilibrium, 1988 Apr. 22 (Box 155)
    - On a Keynes biography, undated (Box 155)
    - On hysteresis, undated (Box 155)
    - On Leon Walras, undated (Box 155)
    - On Maurice Dobb, undated (Box 155)
    - On modern central banking, 2008-2009 (Box 155)
    - On scientific methodologies, undated (Box 155)
    - On political economy, undated (Box 155)
    - An open problem, 1993 (Box 155)
    - Optimal compacts for redistribution, 1974 July (Box 155)
    - Optimum property of fundamental formula, undated (Box 155)
    - Ota Sik, 1989 Jan. (Box 155)
    - Our double helix model of heterogeneous capitals, undated (Box 155)
    - Papers on revealed preference, 1996 (Box 155)
    - Comments on Pioneering Economic Theory, 1630-1980: A Mathematical Restatement, by Hans Brems, 1986 (Box 155)
    - Pros and cons of a single best global portfolio, 2008 (Box 155)
    - Random notes on speculative markets, undated (Box 155)
    - Recollections and thoughts on Hansen, undated (Box 155)
    - Reswitching paradoxes and optimal investment programs, undated (Box 155)
    - Rights and wrongs in the so-called two-Cambridges capital controversy, 2003 (Box 155)
    - The road not taken: a fantasy in which Marshall recants on consumers surplus, undated (Box 155)
    - Rocking-horse dynamic models that definitely do rock historic 1800-2000 business cycles, 2007 (Box 155)
    - The role of energy futures, 1992 (Box 155)
    - Scenarios to elucidate fallacies in the unequal exchange doctrine, 1996 (Box 155)
    - Shooting down one more fallacious case for time diversification, undated (Box 155)
    - Short reconciliation between 1750-1870 classical economics and modern pro-neoclassical economics (Box 155)
    - On simple Simonism, undated (Box 155)
    - Sir John Hicks and Kenneth J. Arrow: 1972 Nobel Award recipients (Box 155)
    - Slowing growth favors Pasinetti dual equilibrium, undated (Box 155)
    - Some insider stories about the famous Modigliani-Miller theorem, undated (Box 155)
    - Some reflections on heterogenous intertemporal competitive models, 1980s (Box 155)
    - Short reconciliation between 1750-1870 classical economics and modern pro-neoclassical economics, 2008 (Box 155)
    - Stability of gradient motion to any strong saddlepoint, undated (Box 155)
    - Stagflation II, 1973 Sept. 24 (Box 155)
    - Stochastic choices/Markowitz quadratic programming, 2007 (Box 155)
    - The strong axiom of consumption theory, 1952 (Box 155)
    - Suggestions for a theory of income distribution, undated (Box 155)
    - Theory of Bienaymé-Tchebyshev inequality, undated (Box 155)
    - Theory of income distribution, 1968 (Box 155)
    - The theory of money, undated (Box 155)
    - Third thoughts on Thünen, undated (Box 155)
    - Thünen, undated (Box 155)
    - Transitional effects on lifecycle savings rate when growth rates of population and productivity must fall, 1987 (Box 155)
    - Two conservative seers (Hayek and Friedman), undated (Box 155)
    - The two disciples: E.B. Wilson and Irving Fisher, undated (Box 155)
    - Two queries about utility and game theory, undated (Box 155)
    - An upper-bound on utility loss traceable to price distribution, undated (Box 155)
    - One notebook, 1981 (Box 155)
    - Variations on a theme by Samuelson: More fallacies about the Law of Large Numbers (Box 155)
    - Various balanced growth potentialities, undated (Box 155)
    - Vetting Quesnay, 1992 Jan. 7 (Box 155)
    - V.O. Watts: Do we want free enterprise?, undated (Box 155)
    - Welfare economics, 1990s (Box 155)
    - What remains true about capital deepening, undated (Box 155)
    - When the poor might benefit from rich neighbors, undated (Box 155)
    - Where are the emperor's clothes? To be understood is to be found out, 1996 (Box 155)
    - Who's afraid of Virginia Wolf, or of Sraffa-J.B. Clark capital reversal?, undated (Box 155)
    - Wrong and right way to calculate mean return for multi-period investing horizon, 1987 (Box 155)